Finding Aid for Transportation Research Institute (University of Michigan) publications, 1954-ongoing
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Transportation Research Institute (University of Michigan) publications 1954-[ongoing], 1975-1995
University of Michigan. Transportation Research Institute.
1.4 linear foot
03165, Bimu, 2
Interdisciplinary research institute founded in 1965 as the Highway Safety Research Institute (HSRI). Includes bibliographies documenting the research done in the University of Michigan Transportation Research Institute and its predecessor the HSRI. There are also brochures or pamphlets and newsletters including Research, the HSRI Research Review, and the UMTRI Research Review. Also contains proceedings, proposals, and reports.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The publications are received periodically from the unit (donor no. 4796 ).
The publications are open without restriction.
In 1965 the automobile manufacturers, who were strongly lobbying for a federal program, approached the University of Michigan with a $10 million gift to establish a highway safety research program. In 1966 the federal government created a new program to improve automotive and highway safety. The university accepted the funding and with it created an ad hoc faculty program advisory committee to develop the interdisciplinary program of research. The new Highway Safety Research Institute (HSRI) was to have three main goals:
"To assume a recognized, causative role in the reduction of morbidity and mortality rates (in traffic accidents).
To earn a reputation as a center of engineering and scientific knowledge on highway safety.
To make a meaningful contribution to the educational role of the university." (UMTRI Prologue, Present, and Prospects, p.2)
Four million dollars of the original gift was used to construct the building and equip the laboratories that make up the current site of the University of Michigan Transportation Institute (UMTRI). The remaining six million dollars was spent to develop a research program funded through the year 1972. The original gift was supplemented through grants and contracts from state and federal agencies, automotive companies and their suppliers, as well as industry associations. The name was changed from the Highway Safety Research Institute to the University of Michigan Transportation Research Institute in 1982 to more accurately reflect the broad scope of its research activities.
The automotive industry still provides a significant source of funding. UMTRI continues to produce high quality, state-of-the-art research to meet its sponsor's needs while maintaining the integrity and independence essential to both the automobile industry and society as a whole. UMTRI, as part of the university, contributes to the research and teaching missions of the educational institution, while conducting research on specific state funded projects to increase knowledge and communicate information that will improve the safety and efficiency of transportation. (UMTRI Self Assessment and Review, 1993-1998, p.2)
The University of Michigan. Transportation Research Institute publications (1.4 linear feet) include bibliographies, brochures, ephemera including flyers, invitations, posters, and programs, newsletters, proceedings of conferences sponsored by the institute, and reports. These publications are arranged in one series: Unit Publications. All the publications document the creation of and the research done by the University of Michigan Transportation Research Institute and its predecessor, the Highway Safety Research Institute.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Transportation Research Institute.; University of Michigan. Highway Safety Research Institute.; Traffic safety v Periodicals.; Traffic safety--Research.
Contributors:
University of Michigan. Highway Safety Research Institute.
Genre Terms:
Bibliographies.; Pamphlets.; Newsletters.; Proceedings.; Proposals.; Reports.
- Unit Publications
  The Unit Publications series contains printed material published specifically by the University of Michigan Transportation Research Institute. These publications are defined as being widely distributed and may be published at regular intervals. They are arranged by genre of the publication.
  The Unit Publications series (1.4 linear feet) includes bibliographies, brochures, ephemera, newsletters, proceedings, proposals, and reports. The bibliographies, arranged chronologically, document the research performed at the University of Michigan Transportation Research Institute from its beginning in 1966, when it was established as the University of Michigan Highway Safety Research Institute, through 1995. Within these bibliographies the citations are arranged by topics such as general literature, accidents, injuries, biomechanics, emergency medical services, human characteristics, alcohol and drugs, driver-vehicle systems, vehicle dynamics, program management, law and policy analysis, and transportation and marine systems. They are arranged chronologically in these divisions with the most recent research at the end of the category. Under the heading "brochures" the researcher will find, under several titles, project summaries documenting the research done at the institute from 1969 to 1996.
  There is an incomplete run of three newsletters published by the Highway Safety Research Institute and the Transportation Research Institute. All three of these newsletters publish transportation and vehicle safety research done at the institute. The Bentley Historical Library holds three issues of Research documenting the period from 1968 to 1969. Volumes 7 through 10 of the HSRI Research Review cover the period from 1977 to 1980. The UMTRI Research Review describes research from the period 1982 to 1993 and a few issues for 1996.
  There are multiple reports describing research on various aspects of automobile and highway safety, such as automobile occupant injuries or the identification of problem drivers. In addition there are several reports about the Highway Safety Research Institute and the Transportation Research Institute including a report written in 1966 by the Faculty Program Advisory Committee describing the framework and function of the new Highway Safety Research Institute. There are also three reports written in 1985, 1993 and 1998 to assess and review the status of the Transportation Research Institute.
  - Bibliographies
    - Highway Safety Research Institute Bibliography, 1966-1976 (Box 1)
    - UMTRI Bibliography
      - 1966-1983, 1984 (Box 1)
      - 1984 1985, undated (Box 1)
      - 1984-1989, 1990 (Box 1)
      - 1984-1995, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Brochures
    - General 1991-1994, undated (Box 1)
    - Highway Safety Research Institute (Project Summaries), 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - An Overview of the University of Michigan Transportation Research Institute
      - 1986 (Box 1)
      - 1989 (Box 1)
    - University of Michigan Transportation Research Institute Current Projects, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Work in Progress
      - 1975-1978, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1979-1980, 1983 (Box 1)
      - 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - Invitations
    - Michigan Railroads Association 1954, 1956 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters
    - HSRI Research Review, vol. 7-10, 1977-1980, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Research, no. 1-2 and 4, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - The UMTRI Research Review, vol. 13-24, 26-27, 29-31, 1982-1993, 1996-1996, 1998-2000, 13 folders (Box 1)
    - UMTRI Staff Newsletter, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Proceedings
    - Proceedings of the Seminar/Workshop on Methodologies for Analysis of Societal Issues in Transportation, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Programs
    - Twenty-Fifth Anniversary 1991 (Box 1)
  - Proposals
    - Proposal for a Transportation Simulation Research Center at The University of Michigan, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Reports
    - Automobile Occupant Injuries from Striking the Windshield, 1967 (Box 2)
    - Coping With Energy Limitations in Transportation, 1979 (Box 2)
    - Driving Behavior Study, 1961 (Box 2)
    - Final Report of the Faculty Program Advisory Committee, 1966 (Box 2)
    - Highway Safety Research Institute, undated (Box 2)
    - Hit Lab Reports, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Human Factors and Road Safety: Overview of Research at the University of Michigan Transportation Research Institute Between 1977 and 1986, 1987 (Box 2)
    - Identification of the Problem Driver from Driver Records: A Preliminary Analysis by William L. Carlson, 1968 (Box 2)
    - Report of the Review Committee on the University of Michigan Transportation Research Institute (UMTRI), 1985 (Box 2)
    - Status Report 1970, undated (Box 2)
    - UMTRI Prologue, Present and Prospects, 1965-1993, 1993, 2 volumes (Box 2)
    - UMTRI Self Assessment and Review, 1993-1998, undated (Box 2)